<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in a congregation in the city of Exon on the thanks-giving day, Thursday, April 16, 1696 / by a minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Minister of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15049198</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15049198</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1578:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in a congregation in the city of Exon on the thanks-giving day, Thursday, April 16, 1696 / by a minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Minister of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Osborne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XII, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103111:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103111:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In a Congregation in the City of EXON, ON THE <hi>Thankſgiving-day, <hi>Thurſday, April</hi>
               </hi> 16. 1696.</p>
            <p>By a Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Oſborne</hi> Bookſeller, near the <hi>Bear</hi> in <hi>Exon:</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:103111:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103111:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Samuel 12.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Only fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth, with all your heart; for conſider how great things he hath done for you.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF we look back to the eighth Chapter of this firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> we ſhall find, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly deſirous of a King. The Government which God had ſet up amongſt them, did not ſatisfie them: They were fond ef being like to other Nations round about them: They would have a King to Rule over them: They were weary of that eaſie, that gentle Government, which God had Erected; they would have one that ſhould Rule with a more abſolute ſway, and exerciſe a Power more De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotical amongſt them. But this was a moſt apparent affront to their God; it was an ungrateful contempt of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore ſays God to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7. <hi>They have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I ſhould not Reign over them; i. e.</hi> This their eager deſire of a King, was not ſo much a quarrel they had againſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> as it was a daring affront to God himſelf, who had placed them under that ſort of Government by Judges.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>chap.</hi> 12th. <hi>verſe</hi> 1. we have an account of <hi>Samuel</hi>'s diſcourſe to this People; in which he tells them, that he had granted their requeſt, had complied with their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable demand, and had appointed them a King. Then he goes about to convince them of their Ingratitude to their God, in their having been ſo impatiently importunate for a King. He recounts to them, how eminently God had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on their behalf: How ſignally he had delivered them;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103111:3"/>
with what wonders of Providence he had favoured them; how he had many times ſecured them from the hands of their cruel Enemies, who ſought their deſtruction. Then in the cloſe he very tartly upbraids them with their diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous carriage to their God in their peremptory requeſt of a King, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>Ye ſaid unto me, nay, but a King ſhall Reign over us, when the Lord your God was your King,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farther to convince them of their ſin againſt their God, and of the Divine diſpleaſure againſt themſelves for ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent a piece of Ingratitude: He calls for a Storm of Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and of Rain, <hi>verſe</hi> 17. <hi>Is it not Wheat-Harveſt to day? I will call to the Lord, and he ſhall ſend Thunder, and Rain, that you may perceive, and ſee that your wickedneſs is great, which ye have done in the ſight of the Lord, in asking you a King.</hi> And immediately ſuch a ſtorm of Thunder, and Rain, was ſent from Heaven, which was ſomewhat unuſual in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys in time of Harveſt, as ſome aſſure us. This Judgment ſomewhat awakened them; hereupon they addreſs <hi>Samuel</hi> to intercede with God for them, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. <hi>And all the people ſaid unto</hi> Samuel, <hi>pray for thy Servants unto the Lord thy God, that we die not, for we have added to all our ſins this Evil, to ask us a King. Samuel</hi> tells them, that he would become a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicant on their behalf. For, ſays he, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould ſin againſt the Lord, in ceaſing to pray for you.</hi> As if he had ſaid, I am ſenſible that it is my unqueſtionable duty to pray for you; as I am a man, an Iſraelite, a Miniſter, I am obliged to do this for you. Nay, ſo far was he from putting them off with a Denial, that he would not only pray for them, which was part of his Office, but as a faithful Miniſter, he would likewiſe inſtruct, and adviſe them for their advantage, and happineſs; he would diſcover to them what courſe they ſhould take, what methods they ſhould purſue, to become a peaceful, a proſperous, and a flouriſhing People. Therefore he ſays, <hi>I will teach you the good, and the right way:</hi> A way far beyond any thing of the beſt Humane Politicks whatever; a Method, for ſafety, and ſettlement, far ſurmounting any thing they could poſſibly contrive And this way he lays before them in the words of my Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Only fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth, with all your heart;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103111:3"/>
for conſider how great things he hath done for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words you have theſe things conſiderable; as</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Exhortation to a duty. <hi>Fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth, with all your heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Exhortation you may again conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The <hi>Matter</hi> exhorted to; which is, to fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth, <hi>i. e.</hi> They were to worſhip him with a Worſhip of his own preſcription, and of Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) You have the <hi>Manner</hi> preſcribed, how this duty is to be performed; <hi>with all the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You have the Encouraging Motive laid down to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to the more careful diſcharge of this preſcribed duty; and that in thoſe words; <hi>For conſider how great things he hath done for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the words I would preſent you with this Truth to be the ſubject of a ſhort Diſcourſe; <hi>viz</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> That the conſideration of thoſe great things which God has done for a People, ſhould be a powerful Argument to induce them to fear, and ſerve him in truth, and with all their hearts.</q>
VVhat I have to ſay upon this ſubject, I ſhall confine to theſe following Generals. As,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) I ſhall briefly ſhew you what we are here to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by fearing, and ſerving of God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) VVhat it may import to ſerve God in truth, and with all the heart.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Prove that the Conſideration of the great things God has done for a people ſhould be a powerful Argument to perſuade them to ſerve God in Truth, and with all the Heart.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Shall make ſome practical improvement of it.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) I ſhall briefly ſhew you what we are here to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by fearing, and ſerving of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not at preſent detain you with a diſcourſe about the various ſignifications of the word <hi>[fear]</hi> it will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for my preſent purpoſe to prove to you that this word many times in the Sacred Scriptures, is of ſo ample
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103111:4"/>
a ſignification, as to denote the whole worſhip of God. Thus, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>And now</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God? i. e.</hi> to adore, and worſhip him in oppoſition to all Heatheniſh Idolatries, and falſe-worſhip. And thus, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. <hi>Oh! fear the Lord, ye his Saints, i. e.</hi> Pay him all the reſpect, the reverence, and adoration which is his due; Thus <hi>Deut</hi> 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt ſwear by his Name.</hi> What we are here to underſtand by <hi>the fearing of God,</hi> may be learnt from thoſe words of our Saviour; which are a comment upon this Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> Here our Lord explains the word <hi>[fear]</hi> by worſhip; So that frequently in the ſacred wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings we meet with the word <hi>[fear]</hi> importing the whole worſhip of God. In this ſenſe are we to take the word <hi>[fear]</hi> in the Text: And the following word <hi>[ſerve]</hi> is Exegetical of the former, and likewiſe ſhews, that by the word <hi>[fear]</hi> we are to underſtand a worſhipping, and an adoring of the True God.</p>
            <p>Then as to the word <hi>[ſerve]</hi> it alſo imports the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, look back but to <hi>verſe</hi> 10. of this Chapter, and hence you may learn the meaning of this word. For there is it ſaid; <hi>And they cryed to the Lord, and ſaid, we have ſinned, becauſe we have forſaken the Lord, and have ſerved</hi> Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim <hi>and</hi> Aſhtaroth; <hi>But now deliver us out of the hands of our Enemies, and we will ſerve thee.</hi> Where the <hi>ſerving</hi> of God is put in oppoſition to the <hi>ſerving</hi> of <hi>Baalim,</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> and ſo plainly denotes the worſhipping of God. So that the thing which <hi>Samuel</hi> here preſſes the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to, is the paying that homage, that honour, and adoration to the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to the only immortal God, which are his due. He would have them to give over the worſhipping their <hi>Baalim,</hi> and their <hi>Aſhtaroth;</hi> to renounce all Heathen Deities, and to betake themſelves intirely to the ſervice of the only True God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) I am to explain what it does import to <hi>ſerve, and fear God in truth, and with all the Heart.</hi> And here,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) What it is to ſerve, and worſhip God <hi>in truth.</hi> Now to ſerve God <hi>in truth</hi> is to worſhip him in a way, and a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his own appointment. It is to preſent him him with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103111:4"/>
ſuch ſervices as he himſelf has Authorized. So that it is put in oppoſition to all falſe worſhip. For <hi>Samuel</hi> does here caution the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> againſt all Idolatrous, and Superſtitious uſages; againſt all kind of worſhip that has not the ſtamp of Divine Authority put upon it, for no worſhip can be pleaſing to God, but what can plead a Divine warrant. Whatever pompous Devotions, and gaudy Ceremonies men may adopt into their worſhip, if they cannot ſhew a Commiſſion from Heaven for them, God will abhor them, altho their eſteem may be ne're ſo much buoyed up by Mens approbation, and applauſe. God's will, and command is the Rule of worſhip, not Mens teeming fancies; Therefore it is a ſin againſt God, an affront to his Soveraignty for any man, or any ſociety of Men, to uſe any othet ſort of worſhip, than that God has legitimated by his own Command. Wherefore God rebuking the ſinful complyance of the Jews with the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip of the Heathen nations condemns their practices, as ſinful, becauſe they were not bottom'd upon any command of his, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 19.5. <hi>They have built alſo the high places of</hi> Baal, <hi>to burn their Sons with fire, for burnt-offerings unto</hi> Baal; <hi>which I commanded not, nor ſpake it, neither came it into my mind.</hi> They had no injunction from God for the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting ſuch a kind of worſhip, that was enough to render it unlawful. They acted without a Commiſſion, therefore was it falſe worſhip, and ſore diſpleaſing to God. Now wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may be falſe. Either,
<list>
                  <item>(1.) With reſpect to the <hi>Object.</hi> Or,</item>
                  <item>(2.) With reſpect to the <hi>Medium of Worſhip.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Worſhip may be falſe with reſpect to the <hi>Object</hi> of it. As when perſons terminate that worſhip, which is only due to the great God, on any Created, and finite being, when they pay that homage and adoration to the Creature, which ought entirely to be confin'd to the glorious Creator: either when they limit their Devotions to the Creature, with a total neglect of the Almighty God; and ſubſtitute ſome other perſon, or thing in his Room to be the <hi>Object</hi> of their Religious adorations. Thus ſome beſotted wretches worſhip the Devil; pay their homage to the Prince of Darkneſs, as if <hi>He were</hi> the God who made them Apiece of Idolatry practiſed amongſt many of the Inhabitants of <hi>Florida:</hi> and the Natives of <hi>Virginia,</hi> were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103111:5"/>
formerly no ſtrangers to it, and generally in the <hi>Southern A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi> they have ſet up the deſtroyer of Souls for their Deitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lactant. de origin. error. <hi>Cap. 14.</hi>
               </note>Some have worſhipped the Hoſts of Heaven, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars. Nay, the Jews themſelves, tho' inſtructed in the true worſhip of God, became ſo ſottiſh as to take up this piece of Idolatry in imitation of their Heathen Neighbours: for it is ſaid, <hi>Jer.</hi> 19.13. <hi>And the houſes of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and the houſes of the Kings of</hi> Judah <hi>ſhall be defiled as the place of</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>becauſe of all the houſes upon whoſe roofs they have burnt Incenſe unto all the Host of Heaven.</hi> Strange! that a people favoured with ſo many ſtupendious Miracles, to render the belief of the Meſſages of God to them the more eaſie, ſhould be ſo ſoon drawn away to the worſhipping of the Celeſtial Luminaries! one would have thought that the many excellent priveledges they were bleſſed with beyond others; and the excellent informations they had from the inſpired Prophets, ſhould have ſufficiently fortified them againſt ſo groſs a piece of Idolatry. But we are told, 2 Kings 17.16. That <hi>they left all the Commandments of the Lord their God, and made them Molten Images, even two Calves, and made a grove, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped all the Hoſt of Heaven, and ſerved</hi> Baal.</p>
            <p>Others, as the antient <hi>Perſians</hi> have ſet up Fire for their God, and with a blind Zeal have paid it their Devotions. <hi>Matth. Theat. Hiſtor. p.</hi> 13. ſays, <hi>Chaldaei ignem ſacrum pro Deo coluerunt;</hi> that the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> alſo worſhipped ſacred Fire; and he aſſigns the reaſon of it. <hi>Cum enim audierant Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificia à Sanctis Patriarchis oblata, Igne coelitûs delapſo Incenſa, &amp; conſumpta eſſe; non Deum, cujus potentiâ illud fiebat, ſed ipſum Ignem colere ſtolidi ceperunt.</hi> They paid this Reverence to the Element of Fire, becauſe they had heard that it conſumed the Sacrifices which were offered up by the antient Patriarchs.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> on the contrary, choſe out the Element of Water for their Deity; and ſo made their devout Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to the Banks of their famous <hi>Nilus.</hi> Hereupon, ſays <hi>Julius Firmicus, de Errore, Prof. Relig. p.</hi> 2. <hi>Aegypti incolae Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum beneficia percipientes, Aquam colunt, Aquis ſupplicant, Aquas
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103111:5"/>
ſuperſtirioſâ votorum continuatione venerantur.</hi> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> perceiving the great advantages of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Water, worſhip the Waters,<note place="margin">Vid. Caelſi Rhodigini lectiones Antiquas. p. <hi>1489.</hi>
               </note> pray to them, and addreſs them with their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated ſuperſtitious Vows.</p>
            <p>Others again, altho' they worſhip God, yet they admit ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angels, or Men, or ſome other creature, to ſhare with God in their devotional Addreſſes. Thus many amongſt the Heathens have adored ſinful Men, whoſe Vices gave them their Divinity, and whoſe Crimes were their Conſecrations. <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> were numbred amongſt their Deities, and had their reſpective Homages paid them. <hi>Vid. Caecil. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. de Idolorum vanitat. p.</hi> 2. and <hi>Minut. Faelix. de Idolorum vanitat. p.</hi> 27. ſays <hi>ſanê, &amp; Acca Larentia, &amp; Flora, Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices propudioſae, inter Romanorum Deos computandae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others have adored Men famous for their Virtue, or emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for ſome notable Exploits, or ſome remarkable At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements. Thus the Heathens advanced their <hi>Hero's</hi> into the number of their Gods, and the Papiſts pay Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to their Cannonized Saints: For nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with theſe latter, than to addreſs their ſupplications to St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſuch a Worſhip as this is falſe-worſhip, becauſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated upon a wrong Object; and is a moſt apparent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to the great God, who will not have this honour given to another, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. <hi>I am the Lord, that is my Name, and my glory will I not give to another.</hi> To pay a Religious reſpect to any other than God, is an expreſs violation of the firſt command; which peremptorily ſays, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me.</hi> The Worſhip of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of old, which was of this ſort, was therefore cenſured by our Saviour with an, <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what,</hi> John 4.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> well knowing the temper of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> how prone they were to relapſe into Idolatries; how ready to preſent their Devotions to the Heathen Deities, does here adviſe them to ſerve God in truth, with an utter rejection of all the Heathen Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s whatever. He would have them to confine their Worſhip only to the true God, to the glorious <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in oppoſition to all falſe Gods, and <hi>Gentile</hi> Deities. For God is the only proper Object of Religious Worſhip;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103111:6"/>
therefore, ſays our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought to worſhip him excluſively, without admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any into Partnerſhip with him. For he will not ſuffer a Rival in his Honour, <hi>Pſal</hi> 50.15. <hi>Call upon me</hi> (not upon a Saint, or an Angel) <hi>in the day of trouble, and I will deliver thee.</hi> None have power to ſave as God, therefore none ſhould have ſuch honour as he.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Worſhip may be falſe as to the <hi>Medium</hi> of it. God has declared in his ſacred Word, in what way, and by what means he will be honoured, and adored. He knows what ways of Worſhip are moſt ſuitable to his own Nature, and ſo what will be moſt acceptable to himſelf: Therefore it is no way reaſonable that in theſe matters every man ſhould be left to his own wild fancy. For we find from experience, that when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have taken upon them a liberty, or licence rather, to preſcribe Modes of Worſhip, they have fixed upon ſuch trifling, ſuch ludicrous, and ſometimes barbarous Rites, as nothing comport with ſo holy, ſo merciful, ſo awful a Being as God is; ſo that God himſelf has all the reaſon to determine of thoſe Modes by which he will be honoured, and adored. And he has poſitively preſcribed the way in which he will have men to pay him Homage. As our Worſhip muſt be confined to God, as the ſolitary Object of it; ſo the way of it muſt be limited by his ſacred Will. Men muſt not make their own Imaginations the Rule of Worſhip. That is not currant Coin which has not <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image and Superſcription upon it; and that is not true and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable Worſhip, which has not the ſtamp of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority. God has ſet us bounds in the Matter of his Worſhip, to which we dare not make any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and from which we are not allowed to make any defalcations, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Ye ſhall not add to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103111:6"/>
Word, which I command you, neither ſhall ye diminiſh ought from it, that ye may keep the Commandments of the Lord your God, which I command you.</hi> A like paſſage you find, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>What thing ſoever I command you, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to do it, thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</hi> God will not allow any Men to make either additions to, or ſubſtractions from his own Worſhip. If Men ſubſtract from the Worſhip of God, and wilfully neglect what he has preſcribed, they daringly affront his Soveraignty, and quarrel at his Commands. If they add to his Inſtitutions, and appoint more parts of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip than he has done, they arraign his Wiſdom; as if he had not contrived wiſely enough for his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; as if he wanted wiſdom for the Inſtituting of his own Worſhip. It ſavours of an intolerable piece of Arrogancy for any Man to preſume, that he can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to God, or make any advantageous additions to his own Appointments. Such an one forgets the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſs of his own Intellectuals, as well as the All-comprehenſiveneſs of the Divine VViſdom. He does but diſplay his own folly, who goes about to teach the Omniſcient Deity what ought to be adopted into his VVorſhip. But to conclude this; God muſt not be worſhipped according to the little Model of our fancies, but according to his own Appointments. Not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Inventions, but his own Inſtitutions; not according to our Imaginations, but according to the Line of his own Revelations; not according to Men's extravagant ſuggeſtions, but his own wiſe preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. VVhoever offers to God a VVorſhip which he has not authorized, does not ſerve him, but rather af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him. Hence it was that <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſtudying, and deſigning the good and welfare of the Iſraelitiſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, adviſes them to offer to God a true VVorſhip, a VVorſhip which he would approve, and accept;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103111:7"/>
that ſo he might ſtill continue to be their propitious Governour, and their bountiful Benefactor.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) As perſons muſt worſhip God with a worſhip that is true, as to the matter of it, ſo it muſt be right as to the manner; it muſt be offered to the glorious Object of it with all the heart. As fearing, and ſerving of God in truth, is here in my text, put in oppoſition to all falſe worſhip, ſo I humbly conceive, the ſerving of God with all the heart, is put in oppoſition to all diſſimulation, and Hypocriſie. Too many worſhip God with their bodies, when their hearts are eſtranged from him. They offer him the outward Man, and deny him the Soul; Preſent him with the Carcaſs of devotion, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is no ſpirit to animate it. They give him the bended knee, and the hand lifted up, whilſt their minds are wandring after Vanity. Of ſuch kind of worſhippers as theſe is the complaint, Matth. 15.8, 9. <hi>This people draweth nigh to me with their mouths, and honoureth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</hi> Were there no more bodies, ſometimes in the moſt thronged Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, then there are Souls, how ſmall would the number be? How often do men diſſemble in their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and offer to their God a skin inſtead of a Sacrifice; ſo that altho their worſhip may be pompous, yet it is not ſincere, and will not meet with acceptance from him, who looks beyond the ſurface, and penetrates the very ſecrets of the Soul. God does not only expect that worſhip men preſent him ſhould be true, as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but ſincere, as to the manner. Some in the Duties of Religion are juſt like a perſon who takes his Scabbard, and offers it to his prince but imploys his ſword in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſervice. They will bring their bodies into the places of worſhip, and put them in a poſture of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, whilſt their affections perhaps ſhall be committing folly with ſome darling Idol, erected in the fancy. But in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103111:7"/>
vain do ſuch worſhippers preſume upon accepta nce. An all-ſeeing eye eaſily diſcerns the fallacie, and a God of truth abominates it. When the Soul, the choiceſt part of man, as Ingaged in his worſhip, is actively imployed in his ſervice, then does he ſmell a ſweet ſavour in it, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.26. <hi>My Son give, me thy heart.</hi> In all the Solemn and Sacred duties, which men do perform, in all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions they preſent to their God, he demands their hearts and affections; without which, all the moſt glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering ſhews, and gaudy pretences imaginable will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no more than a ſpecious vanity. <hi>Lactantius. de. juſtit. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. ſpeaking of the excellency of the Chriſtian Religion as unconceivably ſurmounting that of the Heathen, ſays, <hi>Illic nihil exigitur aliud, quam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis pecudum, &amp; fumus, &amp; inepta libatio, hic bona mens, purum pectus, innocens vita,</hi> Go amongſt the Heathens and there is nothing but the blood of beaſts, a little vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſmoke, and ridiculous Sacrificing: but with us there is a good mind, a pure heart, and an innocent life. The Chriſtians preſented God not with ſlain beaſts, but with pure hearts: And ſays the ſame Author, juſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Noſtra Religio tota in animo colentis eſt, quia mentem ipſam pro Sacrificio habet;</hi> Our Religion lies in the mind of the worſhipper, and we offer up our Souls to God for a Sacrifice. But too too many Chriſtians of latter ages have ſtrangely degenerated from the primitive practice, and have ſat down ſatisfied with a few exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and lazy devotions. Amongſt the Papiſts it muſt be confeſſed, they have a very pompous, theatrical wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but there is little of Soul or Spirit in it.</p>
            <p>Many amongſt thoſe of the Reformed Churches are too prone to pleaſe themſelves with ſome externals of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſplendid formalties. But alas! the moſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate external obſervances will ne're attract the favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eye of God; when there is an abſence of the heart.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103111:8"/>
All acceptable worſhip muſt ariſe from the Center of the Soul, for <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> John 4.24. and nothing will pleaſe him but a ſpiritual worſhip.</p>
            <p>Well then the affections muſt animate all our devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the whole heart muſt be found an ingredient in all our ſervices: All the powers, all the faculties of the Soul muſt be ſeriouſly imployed in every part of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we at any time engage in, not only the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to apprehend the nature of the duties they are to perform, but the will, and affections muſt be active too. Every faculty ought to be vigorous, and wakeful, when perſons are making their Religious addreſſes to the glorious King, no power ſhould be dull, or ſleepy. As for inſtance, in the duty of Prayer, the whole Soul ought to be engaged in it. The underſtanding ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the conſideration of God's glorious perfections, of our unworthineſs to appear before him, of the many wants we labour under, and of Gods (both) ability &amp; readineſs to ſupply all our neceſſities. The will ought to be engaged in purpoſing the renuntiation of the ſins which we own in confeſſion, and in reſolving a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the duties, which we beg the grace to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. Our affections ſhould all be ſhining, and active, when we view over the glorious perfections of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, ſuch as Almightineſs, Immenſity, Infinite knowledge, Juſtice, and holineſs; we ſhould call up the paſſion of fear, ſee to have our minds poſſeſſed with a Reverential awe at the thoughts of ſo termendous a Majeſty. When we recount his Grace, and his Mercy, his Goodneſs and his Bounty, our Souls ſhould be enflamed with love. Our hatred ſhould riſe againſt ſin when we acknowledge it, with its heightning circumſtances; and our deſires ſhould be carried out with a great deal of warmth after grace, and glory. Thus, when the powers of the Soul have each their reſpective activities in duty, then is God ſerved with all the heart.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103111:8"/>(3.) The third particular I propoſed to ſpeak to, is the Motive imployed to inforce the duty preſcribed. The conſideration of the great things which God has done for a people, ſhould be a powerful argument with them to induce them to ſerve the Lord in truth, and with all the heart. The Command of God does oblige, and ſhould engage perſons to ſerve, and adore him with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, zeal, and affection. But God's mercy, his goodneſs, &amp; his bounty ſhould be an additional perſwaſive: When God with gracious, and merciful providences attends a people, it is but equitable they ſhould return him A tribute of thanks, and adoration. Signal favours, and ſeaſonable deliverances ſtrongly plead with them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him with their beſt, and their choiceſt ſervices: Such returns as theſe ſhould perſons make.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Upon the account of <hi>Graditude:</hi> Men ought to make thankful returns to their glorious preſerver, and their bountiful benefactor, for all the miracles of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he has ſhewed them. When the arm of the Lord has brought them Salvation, they ſhould expreſs their thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſenſe of it by devout adorations, &amp; a loyal obſervance of all his injunctions. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had an ample ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the indulgent care of Heaven towards them; God in his wiſe and powerful providence often appeared ſo ſignally for them, as that it was to the aſtoniſhment of their enemies, and their own admiration. What an amazing, what a ſurprizing deliverance did he glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accompliſh for them at the Red-Sea? In what a miraculous way did he ſupport, and ſuſtain them, during their long peregrination in the Wilderneſs! In how wonderful a manner did he introduce them into the promiſed Land, and ſettle them there! what aſtoniſhing victories did he often give them over their enemies; when as the number of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was but ſmall, and the armies of the <hi>Aliens</hi> like to the ſand of the Sea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103111:9"/>
God made them formidable to all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about them, Crowned them with admirable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; and made them glorious by an unuſual train of providences. He ſtopt the courſe of the Sun in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens to make the longer day, that they might have time enough to compleat the conqueſt of their Enemies. Many times when the confidence of their foes was advanced, when they threatned high, and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in apparent danger, had no proſpect of an eſcape, then, in their extremity, has God brought them Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now certainly ingenuity, and gratitude ſhould promote ſuch a people, ſo bleſſed, ſo wonderfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſo ſignally owned by God, to fear, and ſerve him in truth, and with all the heart. <hi>Gratitude</hi> obliged them to a moſt punctual obſervance of all his Commands, to a moſt cordial, and ſincere performance of all the duties he had preſcribed them. If God in an illuſtrious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſaves a people from ruine, if he favours them with peculiar priveledges, and advances them above their Neighbours by his choice, and extraordinary bleſſings, it will be the blackeſt ingratitude in ſuch, to neglect his worſhip, or to put him off with a few Hypocritical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions. Is it commendable for a people to trifle in their worſhipping of that God, who has made his perfections Conſpicuous in their ſafety? Where is the Juſtice of it? when perſons are made eminent by their mercies, it is but reaſonable they ſhould give God the glory of it, by the moſt Cordial, and lively devotions. When <hi>Moſes</hi> had recounted the great things which God had done for <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the Red Sea, and in the Wilderneſs, he ſaid to them, Deut. 10.12. <hi>And now</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2) Perſons ſhould make a return of their hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103111:9"/>
to their God, for the great things he has done for them, likewiſe in point of VViſdom; That God might again appear for them in the times of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and diſtreſs. It is no part of wiſdom for a people to affront their God, to provoke their glorious preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or to Engage an Almighty power againſt them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a madneſs in any, after God has ſignally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for, and delivered them, to flight his worſhip, to diſſemble in their devotions, and to mock with an infinite Majeſty; For this is the way to have the divine Providence as Conſpicuous in their deſtruction, as it was before eminent in their Salvation. This will engage him againſt them as an Enemy; who before appeared for them in the Relation of a Friend. Therefore it is a piece of commendable Policy in a People to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Adorers of their God, eſpecially after unuſual, and ſurprizing Deliverances, that ſo he may continue to ſuccour, and ſave them in their Straits and Dangers, he may ſtill ſecure them from the Rage and Violence of their Deſigning Enemies; that he may defend and protect them, when ſubtle Heads, and powerful Hands are attempting their Ruine; that when Plots, and baſe, and barbarous Deſigns are framing againſt them, he may ſuddenly blaſt, and totally diſappoint them. Knowing this, that as God has done great things for a People, ſo he will continue to be friend, and to bleſs them, if they will be but Loyal, and dutiful, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in their Adorations of him. For, ſays God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour;</hi> i. e. Thoſe who adore, and worſhip me with a Religious Fear, and with Devout Hearts, according to my own Inſtitutions, I will honour them, I will advance them to Dignity, I will make them glorious, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. That therefore was good Advice of <hi>David</hi> to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103111:10"/>
his Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>And thou</hi> Solomon, <hi>my Son, know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart, and with a willing a mind; for the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and underſtandeth all the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of the thoughts: If thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>USE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) I ſhall apply this Truth by way of Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and this condemns,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Thoſe who neglect to fear and ſerve God with all their hearts, although God has done great things for them. Many amongſt us are juſtly charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with groſs Ingratitude on this ſcore. God has been pleaſed to Plant the Goſpel in its Purity among us, and has now preſerved it with us for many years, in ſpite of all the Rage of Hell, and Malice of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me.</hi> God has hitherto by a ſeries of gracious Providences, ſecured to us our Civil and Religious Liberties, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our Enemies at home and abroad have been imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Skill and their Cunning, all their Power and Intereſt to wreſt them from us. They have been unwearied in their contriving Methods to Enſlave, and Ruine us: But the ſucceſs has not been anſwerable to their reſtleſs Endeavours, and their matchleſs Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence: No, the watchful Shepherd of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> has obſerved all their bloody and miſchievous Deſigns, and has been as careful to prevent and defeat them, as they have been ſtudious to hatch, and contrive their Villanies. How often has the Divine Providence interpoſed for us, ſheltred us from Threatning Storms; when we were in danger, and knew it not? How many
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103111:10"/>
Eminent Deliverances has he wrought out for us, when we ſaw no Deſign againſt us, till it was ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd viſible by the defeat? Yet after all theſe Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſplays of the Divine Mercy and Goodneſs, how little is God ſerved, or ſincerely worſhipped amongſt us? How do Men trifle in their Duties? and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement with their God by their External Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Men of all Perſwaſions pretend a great deal of Zeal for the Worſhip of God; nothing more dear to them, if you will believe what their Tongues avow; yet when they come to engage in this Worſhip, of which they ſeem ſo fond, how much coldneſs and careleſneſs do they betray and diſcover? Their hearts and affections do not keep them company in their Duties. But, where is the Equity of ſuch a Carriage? What! Has God ſignally owned us? Has he been our glorious Protector? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.2. <hi>Has he filled our Tongues with laughter,</hi> and the Faces of our Enemies with ſhame and confuſion? And ſhall we ſlight his Worſhip? Shall we offer him a dead Devotion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the heart? This will be unreaſonable, not admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the leaſt ſhadow for a defence. Thoſe words of <hi>Moſes</hi> are applicable enough to ſuch ungrateful Wretches, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Do ye thus requite the Lord, oh fooliſh people, and unwiſe! Is not he thy Father which hath bought thee? hath he not made thee, and eſtabliſhed thee?</hi> Was it not he, who delivered us from the Romiſh Yoke? who reſcued us from Popiſh Tyranny? Has he not made us a proſperous, and a flouriſhing Nation? made us great, and glorious in the Eyes of our Neighbours? and Eſtabliſhed the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion amongſt us? And ſhall we dare to provoke ſuch a God with our Formalities, and Hypocriſies, our fruitleſs and heartleſs Devotions? Oh! be aſhamed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103111:11"/>
of an Ingratitude ſo black and inexcuſable!</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) This condemns alſo thoſe, who are ſo far from being encouraged to ſerve God from the conſideration of the great things he has done for us, that they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at, and are diſcontented with their own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. They are diſſatisfied with God's gracious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences. They fret, and ſtorm, and repine, becauſe God has delivered us. Own they will not that God has done any great thing for us in the late happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution. The mercies which God has been pleaſed to hand to us by our King they account their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, and are ready to vote them oppreſſion. They are uneaſie becauſe they cannot be in Slavery. Our ſafety is their ſorrow, and our liberty is their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. They can ſee nothing of a gracious Providence in the King's Settlement upon the Throne. All thoſe wonderful, and ſignal Succeſſes, which God has grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, have not been able to open their Eyes, or to make them to ſee the kindneſs of Heaven to us. A Crown upon a Proteſtant head is the matter of their grief, and nothing will content them but a Popiſh Governour. They would have a King, who is an Enemy to their Religion, their Liberties, and their Peace. A ſtrange Infatuation! that any perſons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Proteſtant Religion, loving their own Countrey, valuing their own Laws and Government, ſtudious of their own Tranquility, ſhould be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch a Temper! whilſt the late King <hi>James</hi> was upon the Throne encouraging the Popiſh Party, viſibly driving to <hi>Rome</hi> with a full Career; then they were uneaſie, till they had diſmiſſed him from the Government; they concluded, (as juſtly they might) that they could not long be ſafe, if ſuch Throngs of Prieſts and Jeſuits were admitted to croud about
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103111:11"/>
the Throne. But now the Tyde is turned, and he that was before ſo much their Dread, is now their Darling; his Return is now eagerly deſired, whoſe Abſence before they could have wiſhed for. Now, it muſt be ſuppoſed, he has been taught more Mildneſs, and Mercy, more Faithfulneſs, and Veracity in the French Court; and is now formed into a loving Temper ro Proteſtants. We muſt now imagine that his long Converſe with ſome of the Moſt Violent, and Cruel of the Catholicks, has much abated his Rigour, calmed his Spirit, and ſweetned him into Lenity. The diſcontented Party would have us believe, that the late King, having been provoked by the Loſs of Three Kingdoms, having been more fully inſtructed in the Politicks of <hi>France<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> having been exaſperated by the ſuggeſtions of the Papiſts about him; is now the better qualified for the Government of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant People. They promiſe themſelves, that he will be all Clemency and Kindneſs to them; that he will be ſtudious of their Intereſt, and they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of I know not what immenſe Advantages which will accrue to them, in caſe he ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. But alas! theſe unthinking perſons do ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget what they actually ſuffered, and what they were farther in danger of ſuffering under the late Reign. They are of the Temper of the diſcontented <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whoſe cry it was, <hi>Numb,</hi> 14.4. <hi>Let us make a Captain, and let us return to Egypt.</hi> They forgat the Miracles at the Red-Sea, and in the Wilderneſs. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God was bringing about of their compleat Deliverance, and their comfortable Settlement, yet were they diſcontented. They would return to their former Bondage. They had rather go back, and lie down under <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s cruel Oppreſſion, than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103111:12"/>
that God by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould deliver them. Thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt us, are ſo lamentably beſotted that they had rather have their necks galled with a Romiſh Yoke, than accept of deliverance from the hand of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, of a reformed Prince. This is horrible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude both to God, and their King.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) By way of advice; I would perſuade all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt us, to <hi>fear, and ſerve God in truth, and with all the heart.</hi> Do not diſſemble with an All-knowing God in your Devotions. Let your affections animate all your duties. Keep cloſe to the ways of worſhip of God's own preſcription. Take not up with any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious dotages of Men. Worſhip God according to his own Inſtitutions, and not according to Mens fancyful inventions See that all your Religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices be ſuch as God does require, both as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the manner of them too. To encourage you to this, I would lay before you no other Motive, than what is offered you in my Text. <hi>For conſider how great things the Lord hath done for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the many favours, and bleſſings which the bounty of Heaven has indulged us. God has planted the reformed Religion in theſe Lands, and made it a national ſtabliſhment. He has favoured us with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent civil Priviledges, and Immunities. He has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued theſe bleſſings now with us for many years, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many daring impieties, and Rebellions with which we provoked him: Altho' we have deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the riches of his goodneſs. ſlighted his mercy, and taken no care to make ſuitable returns to his bounty; yet has he not made us deſolate, nor p rmitted our reſtleſs Enemies to raviſh from us our privelidges either Civil, or Sacred, He has brought us moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103111:12"/>
and wonderful Salvations, when our caſe has been deplorable, and we juſt upon the brink of ruine.</p>
            <p>It was not long ſince we had a Popiſh Governour ſeated upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, ſwaying the Scepter according to the directions of Popiſh Council. Then they attempted to Subject us to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Yoke, and to introduce amongſt us the Idolatries, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. Had we but continued a few years longer under that Government, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability we might have ſeen all our Religious, and Civil Liberties torn from us. For where ever Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery comes, it brings Idolatry into the Church, and uſually ſlavery into the ſtate.</p>
            <p>The deſign which was then on foot, was to have reduced us to the Poſture of <hi>France,</hi> to have made us Slaves, and Idolators. And had not our Gracious God happily prevented them, by the late ſeaſonable revolution; inſtead of a well-limitted Monarchy in the ſtate, we ſhould have ſmarted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder a barbarous Tyranny. Inſtead of Religion, and true worſhip in the Church, we ſhould have been over-run with multitudes of Superſtitious Foperies, and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable devotions. In liew of Solid Goſpel truths to have been preached to publick Auditorys, we ſhould have been entertained with nothing but Legendary Stories from the Prieſts, and Monks, of equal truth with the moſt fablous Romance. Inſtead of Devout prayers, in our own Tongue, we ſhould have been put off with a little Latine Service, with ſome <hi>Ave Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's &amp; pater noſters.</hi> Beads would have been more frequently handled than our Bibles. Inſtead of the Compleat Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, we ſhould have had only a Part of it; the Cup being denyed the Layity by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103111:13"/>To conclude, Inſtead of an Indulgence to tender Conſciences, we ſhould have been Treated with fire, and faggot, with all the Severities, and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that Popiſh Malice could have ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be the Lord, who <hi>gave us not a prey to their Teeth,</hi> Pſ. 124.6. He by a gracious, &amp; an unexpected providence prevented theſe miſeries which threatned us. He ſent, our, <hi>Moſes</hi> amongſt us, to ſecure, and deliver us from our, more, than <hi>Egyptian</hi> Foes. He opporture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conducted our King to the Brittiſh ſhore, led him on, without blood, or oppoſition to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrone, there he ſeated him to the general joy of the Nation, and to the Confuſion of our avowed Enemies; where ſtill he ſits, to the ſatisfaction of the moſt, and the beſt of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>But yet it muſt be confeſt that a Malignant party amongſt us, envy him, his Honour and Advancement, and are troubled to ſee ſo much vertue mounted to a Throne. They grieve, that one ſo fitted for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one ſo tender of our ſafety, one ſo concerned for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, one ſo much an Enemy to an Arbitary ſway, ſhould be graced with a Crown.</p>
            <p>Hereupon they have been inceſſantly contriving how they might diveſt him of his Regal dignity, and give him a remove from ſo high a Station. They have for many years ſucceſſively been proſecuting Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods for the depriving him of his Life, and Throne. But that powerful providence, which raiſed him ſo high, has hitherto been his guard, and defence. It has been glorious in his protection, and his enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat.</p>
            <p>But of late all their conſults, and deſigns were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103111:13"/>
juſt brought to an iſſue, for they reſolved with a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate party of Men well armed, and equipped to have aſſaulted the King in his Coach; there to have killed, and murdered him. Some of them were to have ſet upon the Guards, whilſt others were to have been imployed in the barbarous Aſſaſſinating of his Royal Perſon. And aſſoon as they ſhould have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed their bloody deſign, and have Executed their Helliſh purpoſe, they would have embroyled the Nation, by the univerſal inſurrection of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied party. Then all this was to have been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with an invaſion from <hi>France.</hi> Inhumane vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany! What! to ſeek to take off the Life of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent, ſo couragious, ſo merciful, ſo juſt a Prince by a Clandeſtine Murder. What! to raiſe an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural War in our own bowels! And to invite over the barbarous <hi>French</hi> to execute their horrid cruelties amongſt us! Oh! how baſe! how black a deſign was this!</p>
            <p>But what great things hath the Lord done for us! He timely detected this Inhumane vilany, he has brought into a clear Light their bloody deſign; He has turned their ſubtle contrivance into fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He has made ſome of the Conſpirators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the diſcovers of this Matchleſs Treaſon. And maugre all their Helliſh Projects, our King is in ſafety, our Nation is in peace; and the miſchief theſe Miſcreants deſigned for the beſt of Princes, is fallen upon their own heads, ſo that we can Joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſing with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſalms</hi> 9.16. <hi>The wicked is ſnared in the Work of his own Hands.</hi> Higgaion Selah.</p>
            <p>But that we may the more fully apprehend the great things God has done for us in defeating of this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous deſign. Let us conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103111:14"/>(1.) The perſon, whoſe life theſe Baſe, and Bloody Aſſaſſines would have taken off. The life of a Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Prince, of a great General, Eminent for Courage and Conduct, of one, who, under God, is the ſafety of the Nation; the Cement of the Confederacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the power of <hi>France:</hi> Of one, who Rules us with all mildneſs, and clemency according to our own Laws, and Conſtitutions, and expoſes his dear Life in the high-places of the Field every year, for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and our Nation's ſecurity. How readily does he endure all the Fatigues of War? And to what great dangers does he expoſe His Royal Perſon continually? How forward is he to face the Eenemy in the Field, and to ſtand the ſhock of all their war-like aſſaults?</p>
            <p>He is a King, who ſeeks not to advance his own Prerogative, by trampling upon the Liberties of the Subject, nor ſtudies to make himſelf great by the oppreſſion of his People. But he is one, who makes our ſafety, our intereſt, and our happineſs his own. What a Vilany then muſt it needs be! to endeavour ſecretly to Aſſaſſinate ſo brave, ſo excellent, ſo vertuous, and ſo renouned a Prince? This enhances the crime, and makes it look with the blackeſt hue.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Conſider, what in all probability, would have been the fatal conſequences of the Execution of this bloody deſign; We ſhould have been infeſted with all the miſeries, and doleful Calamites, which are the uſual products of Inteſtine Wars. Savage cruelties would have been exerciſed towards innocent, and peaceable men. The Swords of our Male con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103111:14"/>
would have been drawn, and have been ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a very great keenneſs, by the aſſiſtance they were to have had from <hi>France:</hi> Animated by <hi>French</hi> Dragoons what barbarties would they not have been guilty of. And if a Gallick Army had invaded us, what Cruelties, what inhumanities, what grievous oppreſſions muſt we have expected from them! could we have hoped for any thing of mildneſs or mercy from thoſe, who have for many years, been trained up in blood, and violence; been all along accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpoil, and rapine! They, being our profeſt Enemies, on the account of Religion, they would have thence been animated to have treated us with all the Rage, and Rigour, and Cruelty imaginable. They would have fired our Touns, defaced, and demoliſhed our places of worſhip, ſeized upon our Treaſures, ſlain our young Men, with the Sword, deflowered our Virgins, made havock of our delect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things; and have fallen upon us with all the rage, and inſolence of Papiſts, and Souldiers. For how can we conceive that they would have done leſs, than have acted ſo diſmal a tragedy, in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie's Country? Oh! what man of ſenſe, of hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or Religion would have engaged in ſo baſe, ſo villanous a deſign, to have enſlaved, to have ruined, to have deſtroyed, and laid waſt the Land of his Nativity? Heathens have often Sacrificed their lives for the ſafety of their Country; but here we had Chriſtians, pretended Members of the National Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church, Embarked in a deſign to deluge their Country with the worſt of miſeries. Oh! Unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alelled Villany! Some of the Conſpirators preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it to be the Cauſe of God, in which they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, and that they deſigned the good of the Church;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103111:15"/>
ſo that it ſeems, like thoſe of Old, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.10. <hi>They were for building up of</hi> Zion <hi>with blood, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with iniquity.</hi> So that they would have built their Church with the ruins of the Nation, and have ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented it with the blood of the Slain. Let us learn to rate the greatneſs of the Deliverance, from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Conſequences of the Deſign, if it ſhould have ſucceeded.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Conſider, that this Bloody and Villanous Conſpiracy was juſt ripe for Execution. The Aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines were ready to have diſpatched the King: They were prepared to have given the Aſſault, waiting only for the Critical Moment which might favour their Deſign. They impatiently expected the King's motion abroad, that they might have had an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to practiſe their intended Villany. Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the Diſcontented Party were prepared for an Inſurrection. The <hi>French</hi> were in a readineſs to have made a Deſcent upon us with their formidable Troops. The generality of the Nation began to be uneaſie at home, becauſe of the badneſs of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Our Enemies were confident of their Succeſs. And were little, or nothing ſenſible of our Danger. Thus were we juſt upon the brink of Ruine: But Divine Providence interpoſed, ſuddenly cruſhed this ſubtle Contrivance, prevented the Fatal Blow which was intended; detected the Plot, laid open the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and turned, the Intended Miſchief upon the Heads of the Barbarous Conſpirators. How illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly has the Divine Goodneſs appeared in revealing this Secret Wickedneſs, when it was juſt arrived at the Accompliſhment! Certainly he muſt be wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly blind, who cannot yet ſee the great things God has done for us.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103111:15"/>(4.) Now let us conſider the ſignal Mercies we do yet enjoy, notwithſtanding all the Malice and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of our Inveterate Enemies. Our King is yet in Safety, and our Nation in Peace. We yet enjoy the Worſhip of God without Idolatry; we have Liberty without Slavery. The Sword does not ravage in the midſt of our Bowels. Every one ſits down joyfully <hi>under his own Vine, and his own Fig-Tree; and there is none to make us afraid,</hi> Micah 4.4. We live under the Conduct of Gentle Governours, who do not make us to bend under a Gallick Yoke, nor Reign over us with an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Rigour. They do not Rule us with Rods of Iron, nor Scepters of Steel: But they treat us with all the Lenity and Mildneſs, with all the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs that the moſt diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented amongſt us can poſſibly expect. Can perſons have the vanity to ſuppoſe that we ſhould be full as eaſie under the Government of a Popiſh Power! Can they believe that the late King (now more fully taught the Methods of Perſecution and Severity in the <hi>French</hi> Court) would upon his return, (which God prevent) be more tender of our Lives, our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, or more intent upon the promoting of our common Tranquility? What Man of thought, or penetration can ever give admittance to ſo ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a ſuppoſition?</p>
            <p>Well, notwithſtanding the reſtleſs Malice of our Enemies, Heaven ſhowers down a plenty of Mercies inceſſantly upon us. Let us thankfully own God as our Bountitul Benefactor in the beſtowment of them, as our Glorious Protector, in continuing to us the quiet and peaceable poſſeſſion of them. We have many Eminent Bleſſings both Civil, and Sacred,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103111:16"/>
which our Enraged Adverſaries have not as yet been able by Cunning or Power to raviſh from us. Let our God have the glory of all. Let the conſideration of our preſent Tranquility engage us to fear God, and to ſerve him in Truth, and with all our heart. Let us no more put him off with heartleſs, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Devotions. Let all our Services be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Sincerity. God was real in our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, let us be real in our Duties. Let our warmeſt Affections animate all our Devotions. What greater Motive can be propounded to you, to engage you in the cordial Service of your God, than this great, this ſignal, this eminent Deliverance, which he has ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably wrought out for us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.7, 8. <hi>Your Eyes have ſeen all the great acts of the Lord, which he did, therefore ſhall ye keep all the Commands which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you this day.</hi> Own the kindneſs of Heaven, ſeen in the ſafety of the King, and our own Security, by Thankful Lips, and Loyal Obedient Lives. Let us offer him the Sacrifice of Praiſe; let us magnifie his Name, and grace our Profeſſion by a Religious, an Honeſt, and a Sober Converſation, that God may not frown upon us; but may continue with us the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Time, and at laſt raviſh our Souls with the Joys of Eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103111:16"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Robert Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> near the <hi>Bear</hi> in <hi>Exon.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Paſtor's Care and Dignity, and the People's Duty A Sermon Preached at the Aſſembly of Miniſters at <hi>Taunton, Sept.</hi> 7. 1692. By <hi>G. Troſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt's Aſcenſion into Heaven aſſerted and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally improved in ſeveral Sermons. By the Reverend Mr. <hi>Joſeph Hallet,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Exon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Paſtor's Charge, and the People's Duty. A Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the moſt part Preached at the Aſſembly of Miniſters at <hi>Exon, June</hi> 7. 1693. By <hi>Samuel Stoddon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
